The Life of Muhammadﷺ, The Madina period, volume 1
by Imam Anwar Al_Awlaki
اَلْحَمْدُ لله رَبِّ الْعَالَمِيْنْ ، وَالصَّلَاةُ وَالسَّلَامُ عَلى سَيِّدِنَا محمد وَعَلَى اَلِهِ وَصَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ تَسْلِيْمًا كَثِيْراَّ
أما بعد، السلام عليكم ورحمة الله وبركاته
What was the first project that Rasool Allah ﷺ started when he reached to Madina.?
If we take the four projects, the first four projects
that Rasool Allah ﷺ started with in Madina, these four projects are;
Number one, The Masjid(مسجد).
Number two, establishing brotherhood.
Number three, a covenant that would govern the relationships between the different people of Madina.
And number four, the establishment of the army.
We start with the first project and that is the Masjid(مسجد).
The Masijd(مسجد) was the first thing Rasool Allah ﷺ did, when he arrived to Madina.
And you can notice that it was the first thing, he did when he arrived at Qubaa(قباء),
the first thing he did when he arrived to Qubaa(قباء), was to build the Masjid(مسجد) of Qubaa(قباء).
And the first thing, he does inside Madina is to build Al-Masjid-e-Nabawi(ألمسجد النبوي).
This is because Al-Masjid(المسجد), is the center of learning for the Muslims,
and that's why it was the first project that Rasool Allah ﷺ started with in Madina.
Rasool Allah ﷺ had Dar-Ul-Arqam(دارالارقم) in Makkah, and now he's building the Masjid(مسجد),
which expands the role of Dar-Ul-Arqam(دارالارقم).
Dar-Ul-Arqam(دارالارقم) was a secret location, where the Muslims would meet and pray and teach.
But now since Rasool Allah ﷺ has established an Islamic State,
it wasn't in a secret location, anymore.
It was public, it was the Masjid(مسجد), Al-Masjid-e-Nabawi(ألمسجد النبوي).
How did he choose the location?
Rasool Allah ﷺ was riding his camel and people were pulling it,
everyone wants to pull it towards their direction.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said; Leave it, because it has been commanded by Allah.
So, the camel was going through the streets of Madina and then it stopped in this particular location,
which was a field for drying dates,
when dates become ripe, they need to be dried and they would do that in an open place,
so that it would be exposed to the sun and the water inside the dates would evaporate.
And this field belonged to two orphans in Madina.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ when the camel chose this location,
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: This is our place.
هَذَالْمَنْزِلْ
This is the location of the Masjid(مسجد).
And this is the location of his living quarters.
Rasool Allah wanted to buy this area from the two orphans.
They said: No, we're going to give it to you, O Rasool Allah, we're going to give it to you.
There were some graves in there, graves of Mushrikeen(مشركين),
Rasool Allah ﷺ uncovered those graves and changed the location.
And they started building Al-Masjid-e-Nabawi(ألمسجد النبوي),
they built it from mud bricks
and the roof was palm leaves.
So, when it would rain, it would drop right, on top of their heads,
very simple, the floor was sand.
Even though it was very simple, it was the most blessed Masjid(مسجد), that's where the first generation graduated from.
Rasool Allah ﷺ joined the Sahabah in the building of the Masjid(مسجد),
he was giving them an example of himself joining and working.
So, the poet among them said;
لَئِنْ قَعَدْنَا وَالنَّبِيُّ يَعْمَلْ ذَلِكَ مِنَّا اَلْعَمَلٌ مُدَلَّلْ
If we sit down, while the Messenger of Allah is working
that is a misguided act on our behalf.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ himself was carrying the bricks and building the Masjid(مسجد) with the Sahabahرضي الله عنهم.
Some lessons from the building of the Masjid(مسجد).
Number one,
the Masjid(مسجد) is the first thing that Rasool Allah ﷺ did.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ says;
الَّذِينَ إِنْ مَكَّنَّاهُمْ فِي الْأَرْضِ أَقَامُوا الصَّلَاةَ
The ones, whom when we establish in land, they would establish prayers,
when we give them authority in land they would establish Salah(صلاة).
So, Allah has given Rasool Allah ﷺ and the Sahabah authority in the land.
The first thing they did is to establish Salah(صلاة),
and by establishing the Masjid(مسجد), they're establishing the center of Salah(صلاة).
What is the role of the Masjid(مسجد).?
Allahعَزّوجَلّ says in Qur'an;
فِي بُيُوتٍ أَذِنَ اللَّهُ أَنْ تُرْفَعَ وَيُذْكَرَ فِيهَا اسْمُهُ
يُسَبِّحُ لَهُ فِيهَا بِالْغُدُوِّ وَالْآصَالِ۝
رِجَالٌ لَا تُلْهِيهِمْ تِجَارَةٌ وَلَا بَيْعٌ عَنْ ذِكْرِ اللَّهِ
لَا تُلْهِيهِمْ تِجَارَةٌ وَلَا بَيْعٌ عَنْ ذِكْرِ اللَّهِ وَإِقَامِ الصَّلَاةِ وَإِيتَاءِ الزَّكَاةِۙ
يَخَافُونَ يَوْمًا تَتَقَلَّبُ فِيهِ الْقُلُوبُ وَالْأَبْصَارُ۝
ليَجْزِيَهُمُ اللَّهُ أَحْسَنَ مَا عَمِلُوا وَيَزِيدَهُمْ مِنْ فَضْلِهِ ۗ
وَاللَّهُ يَرْزُقُ مَنْ يَشَاءُ بِغَيْرِ حِسَابٍ۝
"In houses which Allah has ordered to be raised
and that His name be mentioned there in,
exalting Him within them in the morning and evening are men,
whom neither commerce nor sale distracts them from performance of prayer and giving Zakah(زكواة)
They fear a Day in which the hearts and eyes will turn about
that Allah may reward them the best of what they did, and increase them from His bounty.
And Allah gives provision to whom He wills, without account."
So, the Masjid(مسجد) is just a building.
But the real essence of the Masjid(مسجد) are the people inside the Masjid(مسجد).
That is the spirit of the Masjid(مسجد).
So, Allahعَزّوجَلّ says; the house of Allah in them are men,
who are not distracted by commerce, they're not distracted by money, they're not distracted by making a living.
They worship Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
They do make a living, they do work, they do business,
but when they are in the Masjid(مسجد), they are remembering Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
Duniya(دنيا) is not on their mind.
So, the Masjid(مسجد) is a place of prayer and remembrance of Allah.
That's the first and most important role of the Masjid(مسجد),
it's a place of Zikr(ذكر) and a place of Salah(صلاة).
Number two,
the Masjid(مسجد) is the center of learning,
Dar-Ul-Arqam(دارالارقم) in Makkah and Masjid Al-Nabwi(مسجدالنبوي) in Madina
That is where Rasool Allah ﷺ would give his Khutba(خطبه) that's where he would give his talks,
that's where the Sahabah(صحابه) would come together in circles and studying the book of Allah.
Rasool Allah ﷺ says in the Hadith(حديث), if people come together in the house of Allah,
studying the book of Allahعَزّوجَلّ and reading it, Allah will give them four things,
1. Sakeena(سكينه), tranquility,
2.  Mercy(رحمه),
and number three, angels would surround them
and Number four, Allah will mention their names in a gathering better than theirs.
Number three, the Masjid(مسجد) is a place for Muslims to meet, so it plays a social role.
And Muslims who pray Jam'maa(جماعة) would meet five times a day,
that strengthens the bonds of brotherhood.
They also meet on Jum'ah(جمعه)
and the word Jum'ah(جمعه) and Jama'a(جماعه), it mean congregation, people coming together, it's a gathering.
Number four, the Masjid(مسجد) was a dwelling for the traveler, and the poor,
and we're going to talk about Ahl-Us-Suffah(أهل الصفه),
and the special place that was built for them, in the Masjid(مسجد).
Number five, the Masjid(مسجد) was a place where the armies would be sent out from.
That is where the Luw'aa(لؤوا) would be set,
the banners or the standards of war, would be handed out inside the Masjid(مسجد).
And finally, Masjid(مسجد) is place for Da'wah(دعوة),
when the Christians from Najraan(نجران) in Yemen came to visit Rasool Allah ﷺ where did they stay?
They didn't stay in hotels.
They weren't refused, they weren't banned from entering the Masjid(مسجد), they lived in the Masjid(مسجد).
They lived in the Masjid(مسجد), so that they can see the Muslims pray.
They could hold their discussions and conversations with Rasool Allah ﷺ.
So, the Masjid(مسجد) plays an important role, in Da'wah(دعوة).
We said that the Masjid(مسجد) of Rasool Allah ﷺ, Al-Masjid-e-Nabawi(المسجدالنبوي) was simple.
It didn't have all of those fancy decorations.
So, what's the ruling on those decorations to start with.?
The scholars say that Tash'heed(تشهيد) is allowed, while Zakhrafah(زخرفه) and Naqsh(نقش) is not.
Tash'heed(تشهيد), means having good building material, good building for the Masjid(مسجد) itself.
So, the Masjid(مسجد) of Rasool Allah was made out of mud bricks,
but later on, they built it from stone, they had some pillars in there, that is allowed
That was allowed, having a roof made out of wood.
In one of the expenses of Al-Masjid-e-Nabwi(ألمسجد النبوي) that was allowed,
because these things happened during the time of Al-Khulafah-Ar-Rashidoon(خلفاءالراشدون).
But the decoration of the Masjid(مسجد), the scholars have a difference of opinion,
some of them say it is Haram(حرام) and some say it's Makrooh(مكروه).
Now even the ones who say that it is Makrooh(مكروه),
they say that if somebody designates money to be used as a Waqf(وقف), as a trust for a Masjid(مسجد),
it is Haram(حرام) to use that money to decorate the Masjid(مسجد), it needs to go into the building of the Masjid(مسجد).
So, Abu Darda(ابودرداء) for example, he says;
اِذَ زَخْرَفْتُمْ مَسَاجِدَكُمْ، وَزَوَّقْتُمْ مَصَاحِفَكُمْ فَالَدمَارُعَلَيْكُمْ
If you decorate your Qur'an, the Mus'haf(مصحف) and you decorate your Masjid(مسجد), then you would perish,
because that's the sign of preferring symbols over substance.
The Masjid-e-Nabwi(ألمسجد النبوي) was simple, mud bricks.
But the best men of this Ummah(امة) graduated from Al-Masjid-e-Nabwi(ألمسجدالنبوي).
And now we have huge buildings, magnificent.
But what are the results,
they merely show the sophisticated architecture and all the money that was thrown into, those huge buildings, that's about it.
Another lesson Tarbiyah(تربيعة) through practice,
Rasool Allah ﷺ was teaching the Sahabah(صحابه) by practicing.
He was building the Masjid(مسجد) with them.
He wasn't just giving them instructions from a high place.
He was joining them in the field and showing them, what it means to be a Muslim.
The next lesson, specialization is respected in Islam.
And people should be told to do what they're capable of doing and what they're best at.
This is an important thing for the Muslim leader to learn.
Because when they were building the Masjid-Al-Nabwi(مسجد النبوي),
there was a man from Najd(نجد) who was with them.
And this man was a builder, he himself.
So, he asked Rasool Allah ﷺ, should I join you in carrying the bricks?
Rasool Allah ﷺ said, No, do not carry the bricks with us.
You make the mixture for the bricks and make them
and because other people can carry the bricks,
but you need to focus on what you are best at.
And that is making these bricks for us.
So, if this man was carrying bricks, you would have people who are not as expert as he was, mixing the bricks.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ would devote him to this act and have other people carry the bricks.
So in our Islamic work, not everybody has to do the same thing.
Not everyone needs to be a good Daiyah(داعيه).
Not everyone needs to become a scholar.
Not everyone needs to be an Imaam(إمام).
Let people do what they're capable of doing because Allah gives different people different gifts.
And the good leader is the one, who recognizes the abilities of his followers and advises them,
and how to strengthen the gifts that Allahسبحانه و تعالى has given them
and how to take advantage of those abilities for the sake of the benefit of Islam and Muslims.
Some virtues of Al-Masjid-Al-Nabwi(مسجد النبوي)
Rasool Allah ﷺ says;
صَلَاةٌ فِيْ مَسْجِدِيْ هَذَ اَفْضَلْ مِنْ اَلْفِ صَلَاتٍ فِيْمَا سِوَاه اِلَّا مَسْجِدِالْحَرَامْ
Rasool Allah ﷺ says in the Hadith(حديث) narrated by Al-Bukhari(البخاريْ)
one Salah(صلاة) in my Masjid(مسجد) it is better than 1000 Salah(صلاة) in any other Masjid except Masjid Al-Haraam(مسجدالحرام), Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه).
Which means that if you pray one Ishaa(عشاء) for example, in Al-Masjid-Al-Nabwi(مسجد النبوي),
it counts as if you have prayed Ishaa(عشاء) for 83 years in any other Masjid(مسجد),
so if you're praying Ishaa(عشاء) every evening in another Masjid(مسجد) for 83 years,
that counts as one Ishaa(عشاء) in Al-Masjid-Al-Nabwi(مسجد النبوي),
that's how much blessing there is, in praying in Al-Masjid-Al-Nabwi(مسجد النبوي).
Rasool Allah ﷺ also says;
لَا تُشَدُّ الرِحَالُ اِلَّا اِلَى ثَلَاثَةِ مَسْاجِدْ، مَسْجِدِ الْحَرَامْ، وَمَسْجِدِ الْاَقْصَى، وَمَسْجِدِيْ هَذَا
You should not travel to visit a Masjid(مسجد), except if it is one of three Masjid(مسجد)s
Al-Masjid Al-Haraam(مسجدالحرام), Al-Ka'aba(ألكعبه), Al-Masjid Al-Aksaa(مسجد الاقصى) in Jerusalem
and this Masjid(مسجد) of mine, Al-Masjid-Al-Nabwi(مسجد النبوي).
And Rasool Allah ﷺ says:
مَا بَيْنَ بَيْتِيْ وَمِمْبَرِي ْرَوْضَةٌ مِنْ الرِّيَاضِ الْجَنَّة، وَمِمْبَرِيْ عَلَى حَوْضِي
Rasool Allah ﷺ says, between my house and my pulpit
is a garden from among the gardens of Paradise and my pulpit is on my pool, Al-Kauser(ألكوثر),
the pool that Rasool Allah ﷺ would be given on the Day of Judgment and this is in Al-Bukhari(بخاريْ).
Abdullah Bin Zaid(عبدالله بن زيد), one of the Sahabah(صحابه) of Rasool Allah ﷺ saw a dream,
at that time Rasool Allah ﷺ has finished constructing the Masjid Al-Nabawi(مسجد النبوي)
and now they were thinking about ways to invite people to the prayer.
So, some suggestions were using a bell, similar to what the Christians do.
Another suggestion was to blow a horn,
such as the Jews at least in Madina, that's what Jews would do.
So, Abdullah Bin Zaidرضي الله عنه saw a dream,
He saw a man carrying a bell.
So, Abdullah Bin Zaid(عبدالله بن زيد) told him; O servant of Allah, how much would you sell that bell for?
The man said; Why do you want it?
Abdullah(عبدالله) said; to invite people to prayer.
So, the man said; How about if I suggest something better?
He said; What is it?
He said; You say,
اللَّهُ أَكْبَرُ ، اللَّهُ أَكْبَرُ
اللَّهُ أَكْبَرُ ، اللَّهُ أَكْبَرُ ،
أَشْهَدُ أَنْ لا إِلَهَ إِلا اللَّهُ ،
أَشْهَدُ أَنْ لا إِلَهَ إِلا اللَّهُ
أَشْهَدُ أَنَّ مُحَمَّدًا رَسُولُ اللَّهِ
حَيَّ عَلَى الصَّلاةِ ، حَيَّ عَلَى الصَّلاةِ
حَيَّ عَلَى الْفَلاحِ ، حَيَّ عَلَى الْفَلاحِ
اللَّهُ أَكْبَرُ ، اللَّهُ أَكْبَرُ
لا إِلَهَ إِلا اللَّهُ
And then the man waited for a while and he came back to Abdullah(عبدالله) and said;
And when you want to make Iqamah(إقامة), you say,
اللَّهُ أَكْبَرُ ، اللَّهُ أَكْبَرُ
أَشْهَدُ أَنْ لا إِلَهَ إِلا اللَّهُ ، أَشْهَدُ أَنَّ مُحَمَّدًا رَسُولُ اللَّهِ
حَيَّ عَلَى الصَّلاةِ ،حَيَّ عَلَى الْفَلاحِ
قَدْ قَامَت الصَّلَاةْ، قَدْ قَامَت الصَّلَاةْ
اللَّهُ أَكْبَرُ ، اللَّهُ أَكْبَرُ
لا إِلَهَ إِلَّا اللَّهُ
So, Abdullah Bin Zaid(عبدالله بن زيد), immediately went to Rasool Allah ﷺ and told him about the dream.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: It is a good dream, In Sha Allah(ان شاءالله).
رُوْيَا حَقْ
This is a true dream.
Go with Bilal(بلال), and teach this to him.
Because his voice is better than yours.
Abdullah Bin Zaid(عبدالله بن زيد) is one who gets the credit for the Adhaan(آذان).
But Rasool Allah ﷺ did not allow him to make it, he told him to have Bilal(بلال) do it, because Bilal(بلال) has a better voice.
So they both, went together and Abdullah Bin Zaid(عبدالله بن زيد) was teaching Bilal(بلال) the Adhaan(آذان) that he was taught in his dream.
And when he finished, Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) came running.
And he said: O Rasool Allah, I saw that dream.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: Al-Hamdolillah(ألحمدلله), Al-Hamdolillah(ألحمدلله).
And this is an indication that it's a true dream, when more than one person sees the same dream,
this an indication that it is a true dream.
So, this is the story of Adhaan(آذان).
And Adhaan(آذان) has became the most prominent symbol of Islam.
Now a days, you know that you are in a Muslim country or Muslim town if you hear Adhaan(آذان)
So, this is the most prominent expression of Islam, or it's the most outwardly or public symbol of Islam.
What was the direction of Qibla(قبله) in the beginning.?
The direction of Qibla(قبله) was towards the north, because they used to pray towards Jerusalem.
A few months after Hijrah(هجرة),
the Qibla(قبله) changed from the north towards the south, the exact opposite direction towards Makkah.
In the direction of the old Qibla(قبله), they built a shed, a roof
that would provide shade, and the place under it would be called As-Suffah(ألصفه),
it would be called As-Suffah(ألصفه).
So what is As-Suffah(ألصفه) and who are Ahl-Us-Suffah(اهل الصفه).?
The definition of As-Suffah(ألصفه), according to Ibn Hajar(ابن هجر) is;
اَلصُّفَّهْ مَكَانٌ فِيْ مُؤَخِّرِ الْمٍسْجِدِ النَبْوِيْ
مُظلَّلْ اُعِدَّ لِنُزُوْلِ الْغُرْبَآءْ فِيْهِ مِمَّنْ لَّا مَأوى لَه’وَلَا أهل
Ibn Hajar(ابن هجر) says; As-Suffah(ألصفه) is a place,
at the back of Al-Masjid Al-Nabawi(مسجدالنبوي), and it is shaded
and it was prepared for the foreigners, the ones who don'thave any family or any place to stay.
And Abu Hurairah(ابوهريرة) says;
وَاَهْلُ الصُّفَّةِ ضيَافُ الْاِسْلَامِ لَا يَأوُوْنَ عَلَى اَهْلٍ وَلَامَالٍ وَلَا عَلَى اَحَدْ
And this is in Bukhari(بخاريْ),
Abu Hurairah(ابوهريرة) says, about As-Suffah(ألصفه), and he was one of them.
He says, As-Suffah(ألصفه) are the guests of Islam.
They are the ones who don't have any family or wealth to fall back on.
So they live in this place called As-Suffah(ألصفه).
Now not everyone who lived there was forced to live there because of their condition,
some of them chose, volunteered to join Ahlus-Suffah(اهل الصفه), such as Abu Hurairah(ابوهريرة)
because it seems that Abu Hurairah(ابوهريرة) did have wealth when he made Hijrah(هجرة),
but he chose to devote his time to studying and therefore he lived with the people of As-Suffah(ألصفه).
He says about himself;
اِنَّكُمْ تَقُوْلُوْنَ اِنَّ اَبَا هُرَيْرَهْ يُكْثِرُالْحَدِيْثَ اَلرَّسُوْلِ الله،
وَتَقُوْلُوْنَ مَا بَال الْمُهَاجِرِيْنَ وَلْاَنْصَارْ لَا يُحَدِّثُوْنَ عَنْ رسول الله بِمِثْلِ حَدِيْثِ اَبُو هُرَيْرَه
He said, some people are saying, how come Abu Hurairah(ابوهريرة) narrates a lot of Hadith(حديث),
while Al-Muhajireen(المهاجرين) and Al-Ansaar(ألأنصار) don't.
Now we know that Abu Hurairah(ابوهريرة) was late in becoming Muslim.
So, how come he has narrated more Hadith(حديث) and everyone else.
Abu Hurairah(ابوهريرة) is number one in terms of narrating Hadith(حديث) compared to all of the other Sahabah(صحابه).
How come Abu Hurairah(ابوهريرة) knew more Ahadith(احاديث) than everybody else?
So he says, he's giving us the explanation, he's giving us the reason. He said;
وَاِنَّ اِخْوَةِ مِنَّ الْمُهَاجِرِيْنَ  كَانَ يَشْغَلُهُمْ صَفق الْاَسْوَاقِ
وَكُنْتُ اَلْزَمُ رَسُوُلَ الله صلى الله عليه وسلم علَى مِلْءِ بَطْنِي،
فأشْهَدُ إذَا غَابُوا، وأَحْفَظُ إذَا نَسُوا وكانَ يَشْغَلُ إخْوَتي مِنَ الأنْصَارِ
عَمَلُ أمْوَالِهِمْ، وكُنْتُ امْرَأً مِسْكِينًا مِن مَسَاكِينِ الصُّفَّةِ، أعِي حِينَ يَنْسَوْنَ
He said: My brothers from Al-Muhajireen(ألمهاجرين) were busy with business.
While I used to follow Rasool Allah ﷺ on an empty stomach
I had nothing I was poor, but I was still following Rasool Allah ﷺ all the time.
So, I would attend, when they are absent, and I would remember when they would forget.
And then he said; The Ansaar(أنصار), were busy with their farms,
and I was a poor man and I would remember, what they wouldn't.
Because he devoted his life to studying.
He had time to review the Ahadith(أحاديث) that he would hear from Rasool Allah ﷺ.
In fact, he says about himself that I split the night into three parts.
One part, I would sleep one part, I would pray
and one part, I would review the Ahadith(احاديث) of Rasool Allah ﷺ, that I would hear during the day,
while the other Muhajireen Wal Ansaar(مهاجرين والأنصار) were busy, they had work to do.
The Muhajireen(مهاجرين) had business and the Ansaar(أنْصَار) had farms.
While Abu Hurairah(ابوهريرة) had nothing to preoccupy him from studying.
So he chose to be among Ahl-Us-Suffah(اهل الصفه), so that he could go and study with Rasool Allah ﷺ full time.
How would the people of As-Suffah(ألصفه) live.?
One source of livelihood for them, was the Sadaqaat(صدقات) that Rasool Allah ﷺ would sent to them.
When Rasool Allah ﷺ would receive Sadaqah(صدقه), he would send it to them.
And when he would receive a gift, he would take some of it and give them the rest.
Now the Sadaqah(صدقه) you notice that I didn't say that Rasool Ullah would take any of it
because Rasool Allah ﷺ did not accept Sadaqah(صدقه).
Rasool Allah ﷺ would encourage the well off Sahabah(صحابه) to invite them.
One of the Ansaar(أنْصَار) Ya'eesh Al-Ghaffari(يعيش ألغفاري), he said;
My father was from among the people of As-Suffah(ألصفه).
Rasool Allah ﷺ ordered the Sahabah(صحابه) to invite Ahlus-Suffah(أهل الصفه) to their houses.
So, they came and every one of these Sahabah(صحابه) took some of us away, until only five of us were left.
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ told us all to go with him, to his house, and he fed us.
And in another narration, Rasool Allah ﷺ says; Whoever has food enough for two people should take a third with him,
and will have her has enough food for four people, he should take a fifth or sixth person with him.
So, I just want to comment here and say that,
you notice that sacrifice and generosity was part of Islam from various early on.
In fact, from Makkah from day one,
Allahعَزّوجَلّ has revealed Ayaat(آيات) about taking care of the orphan, taking care of the needy, being generous towards the guest.
All of these are Ibadaat(عبادات) that were encouraged from day one.
So, we shouldn't think that being a Muslim does not demand sacrifice.
There's no free ride, if we want Jannah(جنة), if we seek to please Allahعَزّوجَلّ,
we have to sacrifice for Allahعَزّوجَلّ, we have to give and giving was part of being a Muslim from day one.
These Sahabah(صحابه) who were inviting others, they weren't millionaires.
Rasool Allah ﷺ was saying;
if you have enough food for two people, only two people, you take a third person with you.
So, he's telling the Sahabah(صحابه) to invite others to their houses, when they only have enough food for two people.
Rasool Allah ﷺ would take care of them, even though others would come to him for needs.
An example was Fatimaرضي الله عنها , the daughter of Rasool Allah ﷺ, the most beloved to the Messenger of Allah.
She had to do all of the hard work at home
until her hands were becoming injured, and coarse.
So, Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) told her that your father has received some savvy(سوي), savvy are slaves.
So, go and ask him to give you a servant,
so Fatimaرضي الله عنها goes to her father and asks for a servant.
What does Rasool Allah ﷺ say to his most beloved.? What does he say to his daughter.?
Whom he can see her suffering.
He said;
وَالله! لَا اُعْطِيْكُمْ وَأدع اَهْلُ الصُّفَّةِ  تَطْوِيْ بُطُوْنَهُمْ مِنَّ الْجُوْعِ لَا اَجِدُ مَااُنْفِقُ عَلَيْهِمْ
وَلَكِنْ اَبِيْعَهُمْ وَاُنْفِق عَلَيْهِمْ اَثْمَانُهُمْ
In the name of Allah, I am not going to give you and leave the people of As-Suffah(الصفه) with hungry stomachs
because they don't have any money.
And I don't have any money to spend on them.
So, I'm going to sell these slaves and I'm going to use that money to give it to Ahlus Suffah(أهل الصفه).
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ was giving Ahlus Suffah(أهل الصفه) and preventing his own daughter, Fatima رضي الله عنها ,
that shows you how much Rasool Allah ﷺ cared for Ahlus Suffah(أهل الصفه).
Now Ahlus Suffah(أهل الصفه), you know,
we shouldn't think that Ahlus Suffah(أهل الصفه) are these people, who are trying to take advantage of all of the freebies
free lodging and free food and, and they're just do nothing.
These were very active people in Ibadah(عبادة).
These were true monks.
These were students of knowledge.
These were scholars, these were Mujahideen(مجاهدين).
Many of them became Shuhadaa(شهدآء).
For example, among the scholars who graduated from the ranks of Ahlus Suffah(أهل الصفه) are the Abu Hurairahرضي الله عنه,
the most prolific narrator of the Hadith(حديث) of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Another member of Ahlus Suffah(أهل الصفه) was Hudhaifa Bin Yaman(حزيفه بن يمان), the expert of the Ahadith(احاديث) of Fittan(فتن),
most of the Ahadith(احاديث) about the end of time came to us through who.?
Hudhaifa Bin Yamanرضي الله عنه.
And then for example, to talk about Shuhada'a(شهدآء) from among Ahlus Suffah(أهل الصفه),
Safwaan Ibn Baidha'a(صفوان إبن بيضاء ),
Khareem Bin Fatiq Al-Asdi ( خريم بن فاتك الأسدي),
Khabeeb Bin Isaaf(خبيب بن إساف),
Saalim Bin Umair(سالم بن عمير),
Harissa Bin Nouman(حارثه بن نعمان) were Shuhadaa(شهدآء) in Battle of Badr(بدر),
Handhala(حنظله), the one who was washed by the angels was a Shaheed(شهيد) in Uhud(أحَد),
Jurhud Bin Khuwailid(جرهد بن خويلد), Abu Suraiha Al-Ghifaari(أبو سريحه ألغفاري) became Shuhadaa(شهدآء) on Hudaybiyyah(حديبيه),
Saqif Bin Amr(ساقف بن عمرو) became a Shaheed on Khaybar(خيبر),
Abdullah Zulbajadain(عبدالله ذالبجادين) Shaheed(شهيد) on Tabook(تبوك),
Salim Moula Abi Hudaifah(سالم مولا أبي حذيفه ), Zaid Bin Khattab(زيد بن خطاب), the brother of Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب)
were Shuhada'a(شهدآء) in Yamama(يمامه).
And they used to try to make a living, if they could.
Zamakhshari(زمخشري) says that they used to gather, they used to collect the date seeds
and they would crush them and then sell it as animal feed.
So, they would try to make a living but the conditions were difficult,
the conditions in Madina in general were difficult.
So, they were forced into poverty.
What was the number of Ahlus Suffah(أهل الصفه)?
Well, the number goes up and down depending on the conditions,
but they would average about 70.
So, we're talking about a huge group of people
and they used to live full time, in the back of Al-Masjid Al-Nabwi(مسجدالنبوي).
They were very active in study
because they were close to the center of learning, Al-Masjid Al-Nabwi(مسجدالنبوي), which was the University of Islam
and that's why they have narrated a lot of a Ahadith(احاديث).
Some points regarding Ahlus Suffah(أهل الصفه),
number one, the importance of having a social welfare system.
People would stay at As-Suffah(الصفه) and feed at the houses of Al-Ansaar(الأنْصَار).
So, the Ansaarرضي الله عنهم, as we mentioned would invite them and take them to their houses,
and Rasool Allah ﷺ did the same, Abu Bakr(ابوبكر), Umar(عُمَر) Uthman(عثمان) the well off Muhajireen(مهاجرين) would do the same.
So it's important to have this welfare system.
And it's also part of Da'wah(دعوة).
Ubadah Bin Samitرضي الله عنه said;
كَانَ رَسُوْلَ الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يُشْغَلْ
Rasool Allah ﷺ would become busy, so he would turn over the new Muslims to us.
فَاِذَا قَدِمَ رَجُلٌ مُهَاجِر عَلَى رَسُوْل الله صلى الله عليه وسلم دَفْعَه’ اِلَى رَجُلِ مِّنَّا  يُعَلِّمُهُ الْقُرْآنْ
If a new Mohajir(مهاجر) immigrant would come to Rasool Allah ﷺ, this is a new Muslim, who just came into Madina,
if he comes to Rasool Allah ﷺ and Rasool Allah was busy.
He would send him, over to one of us, to teach him Qur'an.
فَدَفَعَ اِلَيَّ رَسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم رَجُلً
So, Rasool Allah sent to me a man.
وَكَانَ مَعَيْ فِيْ الْبَيْتْ
وَعشِيْهِ عشَاء اَهْلِ الْبَيْتْ
So, he stayed with me at home and I would feed him as a member of my own family.
وَكُنْتُ اُقْرِءُه’الْقُرْآنَ
And then I would teach him Qur'an.
So, Da'wah(دعوة) to them also involved taking care of these new Muslims, who couldn't afford, Madina.
Because some of them would make Hijrah(هجرة) to Madina
and they would leave all of their wealth behind, these could be wealthy people,
but they sacrificed everything for Allahعَزّوجَلّ and they came to Madina.
So, it's now the responsibility of the Muslims to takecare of them.
So, Ubadah(عبادة) is saying that
Rasool Ullah send this man over to him to teach him Qur'an, but he also had to take care of his social needs.
And this is very important in Da'wah(دعوة),
sometimes we have people, who come from poor backgrounds would becoming Muslim.
Sometimes they have people who had to give up their work because it's Haraam(حرام)
and then they have nothing, it is a duty of the Muslims to be generous towards them
and to take care of them in their first steps towards Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
Number two,
Rasool Allah ﷺ wanted the Muslim Jama'ah(جماعة), the Muslim society to become organized.
So, he appointed representatives over these groups.
So, Abu Hurairahرضي الله عنه was a Areef(عريف),
Areef(عريف) is someone who would represent his people and would know them,
and would express their needs towards the leader.
So, Abu Hurairahرضي الله عنه was representative of Ahlus Suffah(اهل الصفه).
So, if Rasool Allah ﷺ, had any instructions to give to Ahlus Suffah(اهلالصفه), or he wanted to hear their needs,
it would occur through their representative, Abu Hurairahرضي الله عنه.
And this shows you the organization that Rasool Allah ﷺ instilled in the Muslim Jama'ah(جماعة).
So, it's important that we organize our Muslim communities wherever we are,
we organize according to the need.
Now, we talked about the first project sponsored by Rasool Allah ﷺ, in Madina, and that was Al-Masjid(المسجد).
What are the other three?
Because Rasool Allah ﷺ embarked on four projects, as soon as he came into Madina.
The first one was Al-Masjid Al-Nabawi(المسجدالنبوي).
The second one was the establishing of brotherhood between Al-Muhajireen Al-Ansaar(المهاجرين والأنْصَار).
The third was the covenant that would govern the relationships between the different communities in Madina,
the Arabs and the Jews, and the foreign relations with the people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ).
And number four, the establishment of the Muslim army.
These are the first four projects that Rasool Allah ﷺ embarked on, when he immigrated to Madina.
We talked about the first one, the Masjid(مسجد), now we move on to the second.
Brotherhood is very important in Islam.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ, says;
وَاعْتَصِمُوا بِحَبْلِ اللَّهِ جَمِيعًا وَلَا تَفَرَّقُوا ۚ
وَاذْكُرُوا نِعْمَتَ اللَّهِ عَلَيْكُمْ إِذْ كُنْتُمْ أَعْدَاءً فَأَلَّفَ بَيْنَ قُلُوبِكُمْ فَأَصْبَحْتُمْ
فَأَصْبَحْتُمْ بِنِعْمَتِهِ إِخْوَانًا
وَكُنْتُمْ عَلَىٰ شَفَا حُفْرَةٍ مِنَ النَّارِ فَأَنْقَذَكُمْ مِنْهَا ۗ
كَذَٰلِكَ يُبَيِّنُ اللَّهُ لَكُمْ آيَاتِهِ لَعَلَّكُمْ تَهْتَدُونَ۝
And hold firmly to the rope of Allah all together
and do not become divided.
And remember the favor of Allah upon you, when you were enemies,
and He brought your hearts together,
and you became by His favor brothers
and you were on the edge of a pit of the fire,
and He saved you from it.
Thus does Allah make clear to you, His verses that you may be guided.
And Allahعَزّوجَلّ also says;
وَأَلَّفَ بَيْنَ قُلُوبِهِمْ ۚ
لَوْ أَنْفَقْتَ مَا فِي الْأَرْضِ جَمِيعًا مَا أَلَّفْتَ بَيْنَ قُلُوبِهِمْ
وَلَٰكِنَّ اللَّهَ أَلَّفَ بَيْنَهُمْ ۚ إِنَّهُ عَزِيزٌ حَكِيمٌ۝
And brought together their hearts
If you have spent all that is in the earth you could not have brought their hearts together.
But Allah brought them together.
Indeed, He is Exalted in Might and Wise.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ is telling Muhammadﷺ that it is Allah, Who brought the hearts of the Muslims together.
And if you spent all the money in the world you couldn't have done so,
you cannot buy off the hearts of men.
This was a favor from Allahعَزّوجَلّ
that He brought Al-Muhajireen(المهاجرين) and Al-Ansaar(الأنْصَار) together and made them brothers.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ says about Al-Ansaar(الأنْصَار);
وَالَّذِينَ تَبَوَّءُو الدَّارَ وَالْإِيمَانَ مِنْ قَبْلِهِمْ يُحِبُّونَ مَنْ هَاجَرَ إِلَيْهِمْ
يُحِبُّونَ مَنْ هَاجَرَ إِلَيْهِمْ وَلَا يَجِدُونَ فِي صُدُورِهِمْ حَاجَةً مِمَّا أُوتُوا
وَيُؤْثِرُونَ عَلَىٰ أَنْفُسِهِمْ وَلَوْ كَانَ بِهِمْ خَصَاصَةٌ ۚ
وَمَنْ يُوقَ شُحَّ نَفْسِهِ فَأُولَٰئِكَ هُمُ الْمُفْلِحُونَ۝
And those who were settled in the home and adopted the faith before them,
they love those who immigrated to them.
So, this is the first quality of Al-Ansaar(الأنْصَار), they settled in their home, Madina.
Their second quality, they love those who immigrated to them.
So, they don't feel that these guests are burden on them.
They loved Al-Muhajireen(اَلمهاجرين).
The third quality, and find not any want in their breasts of what they were given,
the fourth quality but give them preference over themselves,
Al-Ansaar(الأنْصَار) would give the Muhajireen(مهاجرين) preference over themselves,
even though they are in privation.
And whoever is protected from the stinginess of his soul, it is those who would be successful.
Allahسبحانه تعالى has protected Al-Ansaar(الأنْصَار) from stinginess in their souls.
This Ayaat(آيات) are talking about Brotherhood in general,
but there's a specific brotherhood that we're talking about here.
And that is the Brotherhood between the Al-Muhajireen(المهاجرين), Al-Ansaar(الأنْصَار)
which started according to Al-Sohaili(ألسهيلي),
he said: Some people say that this pact of brotherhood started five months after Hijrah(هجرة),
while some say nine months after Hijrah(هجرة),
while some say it was established as soon as he built Al-Masjid Al-Nabwi(المسجدالنبوي),
so we're talking about immediately as he set in, in Madina.
What this brotherhood entailed is.
They were brothers just as if they were Blood Brothers, meaning that even in inheritance,
the rules of inheritance would apply to them, just as if they were blood brothers.
An example of one of these brotherhood relationships between Al-Muhajir(المهاجر) and Al-Ansaar(الأنْصَار)
was that of Saad Ibn Rabiyaah(سعدابن ربيعه) and Abdur Rahman Bin Auf(عبدالرحمن بن عوف).
Abdur Rahman Bin Auf(عبدالرحمن بن عوف) was a Muhajir(مهاجر) from Makkah.
He's one of the 10 who are given the glad tidings of Jannah(جنة).
He stayed at the house of Saad Ibn Rabiyaah(سعدابن ربيعه).
Saad Ibn Rabiyaah(سعدابن ربيعه) told him, O, my brother,
I am one of the most wealthiest men in Madina.
I will split my wealth in half and give it to you.
And I'm married to two women, you can take a look at both of them
and choose whichever one you want.
And I will divorce her and after she finishes her Iddat(عدة) you can marry her.
This is the level of sacrifice, that they were willing to go to.
Abdur Rahman Bin Aufرضي الله عنه said;
بَارَكَ اللهُ لَكَ فِيْ اَهْلِكَ وَمَالِكْ
May Allah bless your wealth and bless your family.
Show me the way to the market.
So, he said, thank you, You can keep your wealth, and may Allah bless it for you and bless your family.
But I want you to show me the way towards the market.
Saad Ibn Rabiyaah(سعدابن ربيعه) did show him the way towards the market of Bannu Qainuqah(بنو قينقاع).
Abdur Rahman Bin Auf(عبدالرحمن بن عوف) Allahسبحانه وتعالى has blessed his wealth.
So, very early on, he was able to establish himself,
and he became very wealthy.
He went in the market and he worked and he made some money.
One day Rasool Allah ﷺ saw on him, some yellow color, Sufrah(صفراء).
This was a type of powder that women would use as makeup, in Madina.
So, it was on the face of Abdur Rahman Bin Auf(عبدالرحمن بن عوف) women's makeup was on his face.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ told him;ما هذا, What is this?
Did you get married?
Abdur Rahman Bin Auf(عبدالرحمن بن عوف) said: yes.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ asked him and what did you give her as Mahar(مهر)?
Where did you get the money from?
Abdur Rahman Bin Auf(عبدالرحمن بن عوف) said: I gave her the size of a date seed, in gold as her Mahar(مهر).
So, he has already enough money to buy gold.
Rasool Allah ﷺ, then told him;
أَوْلِمْ وَلَوْ بِشَاءْ
Make a Valimah(وليمه), even if you only slaughter one goat or one Sheep.
These brothers would also advise each other.
An example of that is the Brotherhood between Salman Al-Farisi(سلمان الفارسي) and Abu Dardaرضي الله عنه.
Abu Darda(أبو درداء) was a Abid(عابد),
he was a worshipper of Allah and he was a Zahid(زاهد).
Salman Farisiرضي الله عنه came in, and this was before Hijab(حجاب),
And he saw that his wife wasn't taking care of herself,
in her dress, in the way she looks.
So, Salman(سلمان) told her What's wrong with you?
He is speaking to the wife of Abu Darda(أبو درداء) and telling her because she was Muttabazzila(متبذله),
Muttabazzila(متبذله) means, she didn't take care of her looks.
So, Salman(سلمان) is asking her, Why?
She said: Because your brother Abu Darda(أبو درداء) isn't interested in Duniya(دنيا).
Your brother Abu Darda(أبو درداء) isn't interested in Duniyah(دُنِيَّا).
So, there was no need for her to look good in front of her husband.
Because he wasn't really interested, in anything regarding this world.
So, Salman Al-Farisi(سلمان الفارسي), when Abu Darda(أبو درداء) came in,
Abu Darda(أبو درداء) brought him some food, and told Salman(سلمان) to eat.
And he said, I am fasting.
Salman(سلمان) told him; I'm not going to eat until, you also eat with me.
So, he forced Abu Darda(أبو درداء) to break his fasting.
And then when night came Abu Darda(أبو درداء) stood up to start his Qayaam Ul Lail(قيام اليل),
Salman(سلمان) told him; Go and sleep.
So, he slept.
And then he woke up and he wanted to pray, Salman(سلمان) told him; Go and sleep.
And then towards the end of the night, Salman(سلمان) went to Abu Darda(أبو درداء) and told him: Now, you can pray.
Abu Darda(أبو درداء) the next day, went to Rasool Allah ﷺ and told him, I mean this man had me break my fast
and he had me sleep at night.
Rasool Allah ﷺ told him;
صَدَقَ سلمان,
Salman(سلمان) was right.
Salman(سلمان) said;
He told Abu Darda(أبو درداء) and this was conveyed to Rasool Allah ﷺ, he said;
اِنَّ لِنَفْسِكَ عَلَيْكَ حَقَّا،
وَاِنَّ لِاَهْلِكَ عَلَيْكَ حَقَّا،
وَاِنَّ لِرَبِّكَ عَلَيْكَ حَقَّا
اِنَّ لِرَبِّكَ عَلَيْكَ حَقَّا
You have obligations towards Allah.
واِنَّ لِنَفْسِكَ عَلَيْكَ حَقَّا
And you have obligations towards yourself
وَاِنَّ لِاَهْلِكَ عَلَيْكَ حَقَّا
And you have obligations towards your family.
فَاَعْطِ كُلَّ ذِيْ حَقٍ حَقَّه
So, fulfill the obligations of everyone?
Salman Al-Farisi(سلمان الفارسي) here is, giving Naseeha(نصيحه) to Abu Darda(أبو درداء).
Because Salman Al-Farsi(سلمان الفارسي) is more knowledgeable.
The Muhajireen(مهاجرين) spent years with Rasool Allah ﷺ,
and they have acquired all of this knowledge.
Just want to note here that, Salman Al-Farisi(سلمان الفارسي) was a Mohajir(مهاجر) to Madina,
in a sense that he, came from Persia to Madina for the sake of finding the Prophet,
but he didn't come from Makkah, Salman Al-Farisi(سلمان الفارسي) came from Persia.
But he was the brother of Abu Darda(أبو درداء) they were both made brothers by Rasool Allah ﷺ.
So, the Ansaar(أنْصَار) were very cooperative and sacrificing towards Al-Muhajiroon(ألمهاجرون)
In fact, Al-Ansaar(الأنْصَار), they went to Rasool Allah ﷺ and said;
اِقْسِمْ بَيْنَنَا وَبَيْنَنَا اِخْوَانِ نَّخِيء
O Messenger of Allah, split the palm groves between us and the Muhajireen(مهاجرين).
They were offering Al-Muhajiroon(ألمهاجرون), half of their wealth.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: No.
So the Ansaar(أنْصَار) said;
تَكْفُوْنَنَا الْمُؤنة وَنُشْرِكُكُمْ فِيْ الثَّمَرَ
Then you take care of the work, in the farms and we will split the harvest between us and you.
Rasool Allah ﷺ agreed. And that was the deal,
that the Muhajiroon(ألمهاجرون) will serve in their farms and then they would split the harvest in half.
But even that didn't happen,
the Ansaar(أنْصَار), even though they said, that will have the Muhajireen(مهاجرين) work.
They ended up doing most of the work.
So, Al-Muhajiroon(ألمهاجرون) said;
يَا رَسُوْل الله، مَا رَاَيْنَا مِثْلَ قَوْمٍ قَدِمْنَا عَلَيْهِمْ اَحْسَنَ مُواسَاتٍ فِيْ قَلِيْلٍ،
وَلَا اَحْسَنَ بَذلا فِيْ كَثِيْرٍ
وَلَقَدْ كَفَوْنَا الْمُؤنَة وَ اَشْرَكُوْنَا  فِيْ الْمَهْنَة، حَتَّى لَقَدْ حَسِبْنَا اَنْ يَذْهَبُوا بِالْاَجْرِ كُلَّه
The Muhajiroon(ألمهاجرون) came to Rasool Allah ﷺ and said;
O Messenger of Allah! We have never seen a people like this.
They comfort us, when they are poor
and they are generous, when they are well off.
They work in their forms, and then they split the harvest with us.
We think that they would get all of the reward on the day of Judgment and leave us with nothing.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: No, As long as you are grateful towards them and as long as you make Dua(دُعَا) for them.
As long as you are grateful and this shows you the value of being grateful to Allah and to His creation.
Anybody who does us good, we should be grateful towards them.
Otherwise they'll end up taking all of the Ajr(أجر) and leave us without anything.
And make Dua(دُعَا) for them.
And this is a habit that we should develop,
If someone does you good, make Dua(دُعَا) for them.
If someone has done you a favor make Dua(دُعَا) for them.
Ask Allah سبحانه وتعالى and ask Allah with, you know, with sincerity,
I mean sometimes we just do Dua(دُعَا),
we just do it with the tongue and we don't really know what we're saying.
O Jaza Kallah Khairen(جزاك الله خيراً), O Jaza Kallah Khairen(جزاك الله خيراً).
But we have to do it, say it sincerely, may Allah reward you
may Allahعَزّوجَلّ bless you,
may Allahعَزّوجَلّ give you,
may Allah give you Hasanah(حسنه) in this world
and give you Hasanah(حسنه) inthe afterlife.
This is part of becoming Muslim.
لَا يَشْكُرُالنَّاسْ لَا يَشْكُرُالله
The one who's not grateful towards people is not going to be grateful towards Allah.
This relationship of brotherhood was in pairs, I mean, one Muhajiri(مهاجري) and one Ansaar(أنْصَار) carried on for a while,
until the situation of the Muhajiroon(مهاجرون) improved.
And then it was dissolved,
and the general brotherhood of the Ummah(امة) remained.
So, this specific type of brotherhood was dissolved,
and inheritance laws now only applied to the blood relatives.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ says;
وَالَّذِينَ آمَنُوا مِنْ بَعْدُ وَهَاجَرُوا وَجَاهَدُوا مَعَكُمْ فَأُولَٰئِكَ مِنْكُمْ ۚ
وَأُولُو الْأَرْحَامِ بَعْضُهُمْ أَوْلَىٰ بِبَعْضٍ فِي كِتَابِ اللَّهِ ۗ
إِنَّ اللَّهَ بِكُلِّ شَيْءٍ عَلِيمٌ۝
And those who believed after the initial immigration and immigrated and fought with you, they are of you.
But those of blood relationship are more entitled to inheritance in the decree of Allah.
Indeed, Allah is knowing of all things.
One lesson to learn from this, topic of brotherhood,
A new community was being developed based on a new bond.
In Arabia, the bonds that existed were the bonds of blood relationship,
the bonds of economical relationships,
but now, a nation is born based on faith, it was a faith based community.
We talked about the complication of the situation in Madina.
We said that you had Arab pagan worshippers, and you had Arab Muslims and then you had Jews.
And in this multi faith and multi ethnic society, there were some disputes, conflicts going on.
And we mentioned the example of, when Rasool Allah ﷺ went to give Naseeha(نصيحه) in this gathering of a men in Madina
and Abdullah Bin Ubaye(عبدالله بن ابيئ) complaint and said don't come and bother us with your stories,
war was almost going to break out.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ was now building a nation an Ummah(امة) based on Eeman(إيمان).
Therefore the former relationships need to be dissolved.
So, the Ayaat(آيات) of Qur'an were being revealed to break down the former alliances.
So, Allahعَزّوجَلّ says;
يَا أَيُّهَا الَّذِينَ آمَنُوا لَا تَتَّخِذُوا آبَاءَكُمْ وَإِخْوَانَكُمْ أَوْلِيَاءَ إِنِ اسْتَحَبُّوا الْكُفْرَ عَلَى الْإِيمَانِ ۚ
وَمَنْ يَتَوَلَّهُمْ مِنْكُمْ فَأُولَٰئِكَ هُمُ الظَّالِمُونَ۝
O you, who have believed,
Do not take your father's or your brothers as allies, if they have preferred disbelief over belief.
And whoever does so among you, then it is those who are the wrongdoers.
So, Allahعَزّوجَلّ is now telling the Muslims that you need to terminate
the relationships of loyalty that you have with your tribes, if they're not Muslim.
And Allahعَزّوجَلّ says;
يَا أَيُّهَا الَّذِينَ آمَنُوا لَا تَتَّخِذُوا عَدُوِّي وَعَدُوَّكُمْ أَوْلِيَاءَ تُلْقُونَ إِلَيْهِمْ بِالْمَوَدَّةِ وَقَدْ
وَقَدْ كَفَرُوا بِمَا جَاءَكُمْ مِنَ الْحَقِّ
يُخْرِجُونَ الرَّسُولَ وَإِيَّاكُمْ ۙ أَنْ تُؤْمِنُوا بِاللَّهِ رَبِّكُمْ إِنْ كُنْتُمْ خَرَجْتُمْ جِهَادًا
إنْ كُنْتُمْ خَرَجْتُمْ جِهَادًا فِي سَبِيلِي وَابْتِغَاءَ مَرْضَاتِي ۚ
تُسِرُّونَ إِلَيْهِمْ بِالْمَوَدَّةِ وَأَنَا أَعْلَمُ بِمَا أَخْفَيْتُمْ وَمَا أَعْلَنْتُمْ ۚ
وَمَنْ يَفْعَلْهُ مِنْكُمْ فَقَدْ ضَلَّ سَوَاءَ السَّبِيلِ۝
إِنْ يَثْقَفُوكُمْ يَكُونُوا لَكُمْ أَعْدَاءً وَيَبْسُطُوا إِلَيْكُمْ أَيْدِيَهُمْ وَأَلْسِنَتَهُمْ
وَيَبْسُطُوا إِلَيْكُمْ أَيْدِيَهُمْ وَأَلْسِنَتَهُمْ بِالسُّوءِ وَوَدُّوا
وَوَدُّوا لَوْ تَكْفُرُونَ۝
لَنْ تَنْفَعَكُمْ أَرْحَامُكُمْ وَلَا أَوْلَادُكُمْ ۚ
يَوْمَ الْقِيَامَةِ يَفْصِلُ بَيْنَكُمْ ۚ وَاللَّهُ بِمَا تَعْمَلُونَ بَصِيرٌ۝
O, you who have believed,
do not take My enemies and your enemies as allies,
extending to them affection, while they have disbelieved in what came to you of the truth,
having driven out the prophet and yourselves because you believe in Allah, your Lord.
If you have come out for Jihad(جهاد) in My cause, and seeking means to My approval.
Take them not as friends, you confide to them affection.
But I am most knowing of what you have concealed, and what you have declared.
And whoever does it, among you has certainly strayed from the soundness of the way.
If they gained dominance over you,
they would beat you as enemies and extend against you their hands and their tongues with evil.
And they wish you would disbelieve,
never will your relatives or your children benefit you the Day of Resurrection,
He will judge between you, and Allah of what you do, is seeing.
So, now you have new rules,
that these former alliances, the loyalty that you used to give to the tribe needs to end.
Now, this is talking about the relationship between the Muslim and Non Muslim in general.
But then there are some specific Ayaat(آيات)
that came to talk about the relationship of the Muslim with the People of the Book, specifically.
The people of the box of Christians and the Jews. Why?
Because in Madina, now we have people of the book.
And the Arabs had, this ongoing relationship with Al-Yahood(أليهود)
whether it is a neighborly relationship, or it is an economical relationship
because of all the economical interests that existed between the two sides,
or whether it was pacts of protection, political relationship.
So, Allahعَزّوجَلّ was revealing Ayaat(آيات) to deal with that issue.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ says;
يَا أَيُّهَا الَّذِينَ آمَنُوا لَا تَتَّخِذُوا الْيَهُودَ وَالنَّصَارَىٰ أَوْلِيَاءَ ۘ
بَعْضُهُمْ أَوْلِيَاءُ بَعْضٍ ۚ
وَمَنْ يَتَوَلَّهُمْ مِنْكُمْ فَإِنَّهُ مِنْهُمْ ۗ
إِنَّ اللَّهَ لَا يَهْدِي الْقَوْمَ الظَّالِمِينَ۝
O you have believed, do not take the Jews and Christians as allies, they are allies of one another.
And whoever is an ally to them among you, then indeed, he is one of them.
Therefore, the meaning of this part; He is one of them! is that a Muslim has became a non Muslim,
a Muslim has disbelieved if he takes the people of the book as allies,
Indeed Allah guides, not the wrongdoing people.
And Allahعَزّوجَلّ says;
يَا أَيُّهَا الَّذِينَ آمَنُوا إِنْ تُطِيعُوا فَرِيقًا مِنَ الَّذِينَ أُوتُوا الْكِتَابَ
إِنْ تُطِيعُوا فَرِيقًا مِنَ الَّذِينَ أُوتُوا الْكِتَابَ يَرُدُّوكُمْ بَعْدَ إِيمَانِكُمْ كَافِرِينَ۝
وَكَيْفَ تَكْفُرُونَ وَأَنْتُمْ تُتْلَىٰ عَلَيْكُمْ آيَاتُ اللَّهِ وَفِيكُمْ رَسُولُهُ ۗ
وَمَنْ يَعْتَصِمْ بِاللَّهِ فَقَدْ هُدِيَ إِلَىٰ صِرَاطٍ مُسْتَقِيمٍ۝
"O, you have believed
if you obey a party of those, who are given the Scripture,
they will turn you back after your belief to being unbelievers.
And how could you disbelieve, while to you are being recited the verses of Allah
and among you is His Messenger
and whoever holds firmly to Allah has been guided to a straight path.
So, Allah is telling the Muslims;
If you follow the ways of the People of the Book, who are living among you, in Madina, you're going to become disbelievers.
And Allahعَزّوجَلّ says;
And Allah is teaching us, this rule.
This is not talking about an exception, this is not talking about a particular period of history.
Allah is telling us about something that will remain constant until the day of Judgment.
And never will the Jews and the Christians approve of you, until you follow their religion.
Say indeed the guidance of Allah is the only guidance,
if you were to follow their desires, after what has come to you of knowledge,
you would have against Allah, no protector.
So now, all of these relationships of loyalty are negated.
So, you have cut all of these relationships.
Now what.?
You know, just like with
لا اله الا الله
It starts with negating, and then it affirms
لا اله
there is no god,
so it negates divinity from any deity.
There's no one worthy of worship, that's how it starts,
and then it affirms after it negates the divinity of any deity.
After that it affirms
اِلَّا الله
لا اله الا الله
there is no one worthy of worship except Allah.
Same thing here, this concept in Islam is called Al-Wala Wal Bara'a(ألولآء ولبرآء)
which is important article of Aqeedah(عقيده).
After it negates the relationship, we showed that
Allah is saying that, you shouldn't take your fathers and your brothers, Auleaa(أوليآء) except Allah,
you shouldn't take the People of the Book Auleaa(أوليآء) except Allah.
So, it negates all of these relationships.
And then it affirms, who our loyalty should be given to.?
Allahعَزّوجَلّ says;
إِنَّمَا وَلِيُّكُمُ اللَّهُ وَرَسُولُهُ وَالَّذِينَ آمَنُوا الَّذِينَ يُقِيمُونَ الصَّلَاةَ
الَّذِينَ يُقِيمُونَ الصَّلَاةَ وَيُؤْتُونَ الزَّكَاةَ وَهُمْ رَاكِعُونَ۝
وَمَنْ يَتَوَلَّ اللَّهَ وَرَسُولَهُ وَالَّذِينَ آمَنُوا
فَإِنَّ حِزْبَ اللَّهِ هُمُ الْغَالِبُونَ۝
Your ally is none, but Allah and His Messenger and those who have believed.
These are the ones, you should give your loyalty to.
Your ally is none but Allah and His Messenger,
and those who have believed, those who establish prayer and give Zakah(زكواة) and they bow, meaning they pray.
And whoever is an ally of Allah and His Messenger, and those who have believed
indeed the party of Allah, they will be the predominant.
So now, a new community is being established, a community based on faith.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ says;
مُحَمَّدٌ رَسُولُ اللَّهِ ۚ
وَالَّذِينَ مَعَهُ أَشِدَّاءُ عَلَى الْكُفَّارِ رُحَمَاءُ بَيْنَهُمْ ۖ
تَرَاهُمْ رُكَّعًا سُجَّدًا يَبْتَغُونَ فَضْلًا مِنَ اللَّهِ وَرِضْوَانًا ۖ
سِيمَاهُمْ فِي وُجُوهِهِمْ مِنْ أَثَرِ السُّجُودِ ۚ
ذَٰلِكَ مَثَلُهُمْ فِي التَّوْرَاةِ ۚ
وَمَثَلُهُمْ فِي الْإِنْجِيلِ كَزَرْعٍ أَخْرَجَ شَطْأَهُ فَآزَرَهُ فَاسْتَغْلَظَ
فَآزَرَهُ فَاسْتَغْلَظَ فَاسْتَوَىٰ عَلَىٰ سُوقِهِ يُعْجِبُ الزُّرَّاعَ لِيَغِيظَ بِهِمُ الْكُفَّارَ ۗ
وَعَدَ اللَّهُ الَّذِينَ آمَنُوا وَعَمِلُوا الصَّالِحَاتِ مِنْهُمْ مَغْفِرَةً وَأَجْرًا عَظِيمًا۝
"Muhammad(محمد) is the Messenger of Allah,
and those with him are forceful against the disbelievers,
merciful among themselves.
You see them bowing and prostrating
seeking bounty from Allah and His pleasure.
Their mark is on their faces from the trace of prostrations.
That is the description in the Torah(توراة).
And their description in the Gospel, is as a plant which produces its offshoots
and strengthens them, so they grow firm and stand upon their stocks delighting the source,
so that He, Allah May enrage by them, the disbelievers
Allah has promised those who believe and do righteous deeds among them, forgiveness and a great reward.
We talk about some of the virtues of Al-Ansaar(أنْصَار), the ones who sacrificed for Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Rasool Allah ﷺ says in Bukhari(بخاري);
لَا يُحٍبُّهُمْ اِلَّا مُؤمِنْ، وَلَا يَبْغَضُهُمْ اِلَّا مُنَافِقْ،
فَمَنْ اَحَبَّهُمْ اَحَبَّهُ الله ،وَمَنْ اَبْغَضَهُمْ اَبْغَضَهُ الله
Only a believer would love them, and only a Munafiq(منافق), a hypocrite would hate them.
And whoever loves them, Allah will love him and whoever hates them, Allah will hate him or Allah will dislike him.
Rasool Allah ﷺ says;
لَوْ اَنَّ الْاَنْصَارَ سَلَكُوْ وَادِيًّ اَوْ شِعْبًا لَسَلَكْتُ وَادِيًّ الْاَنْصَارْ
وَلَوْ لَلْهِجْرَهْ لَكُنْتُمْ رِئِنْ مِّنَ الْاَنْصَارْ
This is in Bukhari(ألبخاري).
If the Ansaar(أنْصَار) take one path, and the rest of the people would take another path
I would follow the path of Al-Ansaar(الأنْصَار).
And if it wasn't that I have made Hijrah(هجرة), I would consider myself a member of Al-Ansaar(الأنْصَار).
Rasool Allah ﷺ says;
اَللَّهُمَّ اغْفِرْ لِلْأَنْصَارِ، وَلِأَبْنَاءِ الأَنْصَارِ، وَلِأَبْنَاءِ أَبْنَاءِ الأَنْصَار، وَلِنِسَاءِ الاَنْصَارْ
Rasool Allah ﷺ says in Bukhari(بخاريْ); O Allah forgive the Ansaar(أنْصَار), and the children of Al-Ansaar(ألأنصار)
and the children of the children of Al-Ansaar(الأنْصَار), and the women of Al-Ansaar(ألأنصار).
And Rasool Allah ﷺ says;
إنَّ الأنْصارَ كَرِشِي وعَيْبَتِي، وإنَّ النَّاسَ سَيَكْثُرُونَ ويَقِلُّونَ، فاقْبَلُوا مِن مُحْسِنِهِمْ واعْفُوا عن سيئِهِمْ
He says that people are going to increase and the Ansaar(أنْصَار) are going to decrease
because now we have a lot of people becoming Muslim.
So, the ratio of Al-Ansaar(ألأنصار) to the rest is going to become few.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ says; Accept from the one of them who does good and overlook their mistakes, of the ones who commit them.
وَالَّذِيْ نَفْسٌ مُحَمَّدٍ بِيَدِهْ اِنِّيْ لَاُحِبُّكُمْ، إن الأنصارَ قد قضَوا ما عليهم وبقيَ الذي عليكُم
In the name of Allah, I love you, I love Al-Ansaar(الأنْصَار).
And then he said, Al-Ansaar(ألأنصار) have done their part.
Now it's your turn.
He's talking to the rest of the people and telling them, Al-Ansaar(ألأنصار) have done, what they need to do.
It's now your turn to do that to fulfill your duties towards this religion.
So, this is the part regarding the second important project of Rasool Allah ﷺ, in Madina,
and that is establishing a community based on brotherhood,
so I think it's clear from these Ayaat(آيات).
And what we mentioned, the importance of developing brotherhood among the Ummah(امة).
Keep in mind that Shaitan(شيطان) is always trying to disunite us.
So, we have to fight this Waswasa(وسوسه),
and we have to be aware that the Waswasa(وسوسه) is there.
We have to understand that there's someone plotting against us, being brothers.
In order to fight that enemy, Shaitan(شيطان), who's always trying to cause disunity among us.
I mean, one single word, Shaitan(شيطان) can use it to cause a dispute between a Muslim and his brother.
And that's why Allahعَزّوجَلّ says;
وَقُلْ لِعِبَادِي يَقُولُوا الَّتِي هِيَ أَحْسَنُ ۚ إِنَّ الشَّيْطَانَ يَنْزَغُ بَيْنَهُمْ ۚ إِنَّ الشَّيْطَانَ كَانَ لِلْإِنْسَانِ عَدُوًّا مُبِينًا۝
Allahعَزّوجَلّ is saying to Muhammadﷺ, tell my servants to speak good,
because Shaitan(شيطان) is there to cause disunity among them.
And Shaitan(شيطان) is indeed your enemy.
So, Allah is saying that he could take one of those words that you said and cause your brother to misinterpret it
and then causea problem.
So Be careful, of what you say.
The third project which Rasool Allah ﷺ, started when he arrived to Madina was
what is called Al-Waseeqah(اَلْوَثِيْقَة) or the covenant, the document.
This was a document that was written to govern the relationship between the different communities in Madina.
I will read to the terms of this agreement.
It is narrated by Ibn Is'haqq(اِبْنِ اِسْحَاقْ);
The Messenger of Allah wrote a contract between the immigrants and the helpers, in which he expressed conciliation.
These are the words of Ibn Is'haqq(اِبْنِ اِسْحَاقْ),
I'll start with the terms of the agreement itself.
It says, "In the Name of Allah, the Merciful, the Beneficent.
This is a document from Muhammad(محمد), The unlettered Prophet,
between the believers and Muslims of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) and Yasrib(يثرب), and their followers, allies and supporters
establishing that they are one nation apart from all others.
The immigrants from Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) will maintain their current practice
and will honor Blood Money contracts between themselves
and will treat their weaker members with kindness and justice.
The Bannu Auf(بنو عوف) shall maintain their current practice, and honor their former Blood Money contracts,
each party treating their weaker members with kindness and justice among all believers.
He then made reference to each clan of the helpers, and to the families of each home,
mentioning the Bannu Sa'adah(بنو سعاد), the Bannu Jusham(بنو جشم), the Bannu Najjar(بنو نجار), the Bannu Amr Bin Auf( بنو أمر بن عوف) and Bannu Nabit(بنو نابت).
He went on to say, the believers shall not leave anyone among them burdened by debts
without giving to him in kindness, and in paying for him, any ransom money or blood money he owes.
A believer will not ally with any freedman of a second believer against that man.
Pious believers act against any of their own who practice evil or seek to bring harm, sin, aggression, or corruption among believers.
Believers will unite against anyone doing this, even if he be one of their own sons.
No believers shall kill any believer for any non believer,
nor shall he help any non believer against a believer.
So, you can notice here that this concept of community based on faith, Is there.
No believers shall kill any believer for any non believer, nor shall he help any non believer against a believer.
Allah's protection is all one, the least of them can offer protection to others.
Believers are allies to one another, excluding others,
meaning we are a nation apart from anyone, everyone else.
Whatever Jews follow us, shall receive help and equality.
They shall not be maltreated, nor will help be afforded others against them.
No peace shall be accepted for anyone believer to the exclusion of others, when the battle is for Allah's cause.
Among them equality and justice must prevail.
In every expedition we engage in, riders shall take turns on their mounts.
Believers shall avenge one another for bloodshed in Allah's cause.
Believers who are pious are well guided on the straightest of paths.
No Polytheist shall be allowed to offer protection for the property or persons of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ),
nor try to interfere with any believer.
Anyone who has clearly aggressed against and caused the death of any believer
shall be subject to retaliation for him, unless the dead man's executor can be satisfied.
Believers as a whole shall take action against him, and no excuse for they're not doing so will be acceptable.
It shall not be permissible for any believer who has accepted what is in this document,
and who believes in Allah, in Judgment Day to give help or shelter to any wrongdoer.
Any believer who does this shall be the object of Allah's, curses and anger on Judgment Day
and neither compensation, nor excuse will be acceptable from him.
Any matter in which you disagree, must be referred to Allah Almighty and glorious is He and to Muhammadﷺ.
The Jews shall pay expenses along with the Muslims, so long as they are allied in warfare.
The Jews of Banni Auf(بني عوف) are one nation with the believers, the Jews shall have their religion, the Muslims their own.
This applies to their freedmen and to themselves, except for those who commit sins and are unjust.
Such persons only harm themselves and their families.
What applies to Banni Auf(بني عوف) shall also apply to the Jews of Bannu Najjar(بنو نجار),
Bannu Al-Hariss(بنو الحارث), Bannu Sa'adah(بنو سعاده), Bannu Jusham(بنو جشم), Bannu Al-Aos(بنو الاوس),
Bannu Al-Sa'alabah(بنو ثعلبه) and Jufna(جفنه) and Bannu Shutaibah(شطيبه).
The close associates of the Jews shall be viewed as themselves.
None of them shall go to war without Muhammad's permission.
However he is not there by constraints from taking revenge for injury.
Whoever attacks another may do so, to protect himself and his family, but act not unjustly for Allah condemns such acts.
The Jews shall bear their own expenses, the Muslims their's,
each must help one another against any, who fight those who adopt this document.
They must give one another advice and consultation and do good and avoid evil.
A man is not held blameworthy on behalf of his ally.
Help must be given to those wronged.
The center of Yasrib(يثرب) shall be a sanctuary.
For those who agree to this document.
One's neighbor shall be treated as one self,
without being harmed or sinned against.
No property shall be encroached upon without the permission of its owner.
In the case of any dispute, or incident, occurring between those agreeing to this document
and involving consequences likely to be harmful,
the matter must be referred to Allah and to Muhammad(محمد), the Messenger of Allah.
Allah acknowledges what is very good and very pious in this document,
Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) and those who helped them shall receive no protection.
Those accepting this document must help one another against anyone attacking Yasrib(يثرب).
If they are called upon to make peace, and do so and keep to it, they will be making peace.
If they make similar demand, then it is up to the Muslims to agree except, if the warfare is over the faith.
Each participant shall receive whatever portion is due to him, from his own sides winnings.
This document will not provide protection for anyone sinful or unjust.
Whoever goes to war will be safe
or whoever leaves will be safe.
Whoever stays in the town will be safe,
except for those who have sinned or been unjust.
Allah provides protection for those, who are good and pious."
So, this was the document that Rasool Allah ﷺ wrote to govern the rules, or to govern the communities in Madina.
In sha Allah Ta'ala(اِن شَاالله تعالى) , we'll make some brief comments on this document tomorrow.
رَبَّنَا آتِنَا فِي الدُّنْيَا حَسَنَةً وَفِي الْآخِرَةِ حَسَنَةً وَقِنَا عَذَابَ النَّارِ َ
وَصَلَّى الله عَلى سَيَّدِنَا محمد وَعَلى اَلِهِ وَ صَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ تَسْلِيْمًا كَثِيْرًاَ
وَ السلام عليكم ورحمة الله وبركاته